Guide to the Andrew Putnam Hill Photographs
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Andrew Putnam Hill photographs
1853-1922
PC0004
Hill & Yard
2 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Biographical/Historical note
Andrew Putnam Hill (1853-1922) was born in Porter County, Indiana. In 1867 at the age of 14, he moved to California with an uncle, coming to Santa Clara County in 1868. He attended high school at Santa Clara College, and then studied art in San Francisco.
Hill became professionally involved in photography in 1889, opening a studio in San Jose with Sidney J. Yard. Several photographs from this studio were part of the Santa Clara County display at the World’s Columbian Exposition in Chicago in 1893.
Hill came to the new campus of Stanford University in 1891 to photograph the campus buildings, student life, particularly group portraits and settings, as well as activity on the Palo Alto Stock Farm. His interest in Stanford continued throughout the 1890s.
By 1900, Hill had become extensively involved in the effort to save the Felton Big Trees Grove of redwoods in the Santa Cruz Mountains. Working with other members of the newly founded Sempervirens Club (which included many Stanford and Berkeley faculty), Hill lobbied in Sacramento against commercial use of the area and for its designation as a State Park.
Scope and Contents note
This collection consists of mounted albumen prints commercially produced by A. P. Hill and his two studios, Hill and Yard and Hill and Watkins. Subjects include views of the Stanford University campus, interior and exterior shots of major buildings, events such as the university’s opening day and the funeral of Leland Stanford, student groups, and the Palo Alto Stock Farm and horses. Photographs were taken primarily between 1890 and 1895.
Access Terms
Photography.; Photoprints.
Collection Contents
- Photographs
  - Athletics - Football, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    No. 778 - 1893 team and captain
  - Athletics - tennis (Box 1, Folder 2)
    No. 889 - men playing tennis on outdoor court
  - Athletics - track, circa 1892 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    No. 929 - track meet on track at rear of Encina Hall; faculty housing and water tower visible
  - Campus view, circa 1895 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    View of main quad, probably from Encina
  - Campus view: Lake Lagunita, circa 1895 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    No. 1795 Campus as seen from beyond Lake Lagunita
    No. 5034 Duplicate of No. 1795
  - Class of 1895, circa 1895 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    No. 2031 Class on steps of Roble Hall; students wearing mortar boards; one dog in picture
  - Daily Palo Alto - staff, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    No. 8361 Group portrait of staff; names written in ink
    Brooks, Vanderbilt; Burke, Mollie; Calhoun, Scott; Chapman, Elizabeth; Hinsdale, L. J.; Johnson, Nello; Rice, A. B; Sheehan, Jack; Stewart, W. E.; Wilson, J. F.; Zion, E. R.
  - Encina Gym, circa 1895 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    No. 2848 Encina Gym, faculty housing visible in background
    Duplicate copy with slightly wider view (from 89-152)
  - Encina Hall, circa 1892 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    View of entire Encina Hall - 2 copies; one copy stamped "Stuart & Sheehan, room 94, Encina Hall, Leland Stanford Jr. University” and signed by W. E. Stuart ‘95
    Stuart, W. E.
  - Encina Hall - interiors, circa 1895 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    No. 10562 Guest chamber (noted on back: Prof. and Mrs. Comstock)
    No. 10563 Dining Hall with tables set
    No. 10564 Lobby looking into dining room
  - Encina Hall - student rooms, circa 1895 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Man at desk in room; animal skin rugs
    Two students at desk in room; Japanese fan on wall
  - Encina Hall - students on steps (Box 1, Folder 12)
    No. 2857 Sixteen male students on front steps; '94 and '95 visible on some hats
    No. 2858 Large group of male students on steps, gallery, and porch roof; ‘95 signs displayed
  - Faculty - Earl Barnes, circa 1891 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    No. 11141 Portrait
  - Governor’s Lane, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    No. 8644 Governor’s lane looking north; man on road
  - Library - interior, circa 1895 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    No. 5141 Librarian behind desk and students at reading tables
    No. 5143 Students at reading tables; portrait of Leland Jr. on wall
  - Mausoleum, circa 1891 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    No. 5513 Mausoleum (female sphinx)
    No. 5532 Mausoleum (female sphinx), man standing on steps
    No. 9915 Mausoleum (female sphinx)
  - Museum, circa 1895 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Ninety-five Oak, circa 1895 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    No. 6472 Class ‘95 oak tree, two women sitting under
  - Opening Day Ceremonies, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    No. 6510 Jordan reading
    No. 10128 Jane and Leland Stanford reading
  - Palo Alto Stock Farm, circa 1895 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    View of barn and paddocks from the hills (Hill & Franklin)
    View of barn and paddocks from the hills (Hill & Watkins) - 2cc
  - Palo Alto Stock Farm - horses, Advertiser, circa 1895 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Palo Alto Stock Farm - horses, being walked, circa 1895 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Palo Alto Stock Farm - horses, Electricity, circa 1895 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Palo Alto Stock Farm - horses in paddock, circa 1895 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Palo Alto Stock Farm - horses (mares and foals) in pasture, circa 1895 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Palo Alto Stock Farm - horses, Mary Guild, circa 1895 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Palo Alto Stock Farm - horses, Palo Alto, circa 1895 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Palo Alto Stock Farm - horses, Sunol, circa 1895 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Palo Alto Stock Farm - horses, Truman, circa 1895 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Palo Alto Stock Farm - horses, unidentified, circa 1895 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Horse with groom on right (2 copies)
    Horse with groom on left
  - Palo Alto (tall tree), 1893 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Railroad tracks with tree on right (single trunk)
  - Quad - arches, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    No. 6028 East Arch
    No. 7273 East Arch (duplicate of 6028)
    No. 7333 East Arch, 1891 (Hill no. 9; different view than no. 6028)
    West Arch, men in cart passing through
  - Quad - end of arcade looking east, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    No. 6904 (4 copies)
  - Quad - inner courtyard looking east, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Hill No. 2, 3 copies (SU numbers 7397, 7435, and unnumbered)
  - Quad - inner courtyard looking east, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Hill No. 5, 3 copies (SU numbers 7414, 7442, and unnumbered)
  - Quad - inner courtyard looking east, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    No. 7370 (same two men as in Hill no. 5 but different photo)
  - Quad - inner courtyard looking west, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    No. 6023 (Hill no. 63)
  - Quad - inner courtyard looking west, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    No. 7401 and 7436, duplicated copies of Hill no. 65
  - Roble Gym, circa 1891 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    No. 7694 Gym building with tennis court
  - Roble Hall, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Exterior front of building, two copies of Hill no. 3 and one copy of Hill no. 39 [all same image]
  - Roble Hall, residents, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Residents on steps, Hill no. 1 (2 copies)
    Residents on steps, Hill no. 2 (same people, different arrangement)
  - Sequoia staff, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    No. 7985 Portrait of staff in Roble meeting room
  - Palo Alto staff, circa 1892 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    No. 7987 Portrait of staff in Roble meeting room
    originally and incorrectly identified as Sequoia staff
    Adams, C. C.; Blinn, Holbrook; Field, Charles K., (Charles Kellogg), 1873-1948.; Fyffe, Harriet; Lawrence, George; Sawyer, Houghton; Smith, Carl D. [now Carlsmith]
  - Sequoia staff, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    No. 7986 Portrait of staff in Roble meeting room
    Brown, Hugh; Comstock, Sarah; Cowan, Alice; Crane, Charles; Hicks, Herbert; Holzclaw, Mabel; Hughes, Charles; Mabury, Eugenia; Nash, Kate; Rose, Walter
  - Stanford carriages, circa 1887 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Charles Wooster driving 2-horse carriage at the Barn
    Wooster, Charles
  - Stanford, Leland - funeral procession, 1893 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Procession passing along the side of the Quad; draped horses and hearse very visible (4 copies)
  - Stanford, Leland - funeral procession, 1893 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Procession passing into the inner courtyard (carriage in foreground turning around; RR cars visible in background (2 copies)
    Carriages assembling at side of quad (same vantage point as previous image)
  - Stanford, Leland - funeral, Mausoleum with flowers, 1893 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Mausoleum, view of front and side (Hill no. 3, 2 copies)
    Mauseoleum, side view (Hill no. 4, 3 copies)
  - Stanford, Leland - funeral, Mausoleum with flowers, 1893 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Close up of flower arrangements (horse)
    Close up of flower arrangements (cross)
    No. 5528 Close up of flower arrangements (labor's tribute)
  - Student groups, circa 1895 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    No. 9534 Group of male students and one woman on steps of Encina (?)
    No. 10441 Montage of individual student portraits, men and women
  - Student groups - Kappa Alpha Theta sorority, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    No. 10450 group portrait (6 women)
    No. 10449 group portrait (11 women)
    No. 10452 group portrait, duplicate of 10449
    No. 10451 group portrait, same women, different arrangement
    Allabach, Lucy; Caldwell, Winifred; Fyffe, Harriet; Fyffe, Mrs.; Hume, Mary; Moody, Dora; Packard, Mabel; Pitcher, Louise; Schopbach, Leonor; Webb, Winifred; Yoder, Minnie
  - Miscellaneous photographs, not Stanford, circa 1890 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    No. 14115 five people next to hugh flowering bush
    No. 14116 unknown brick building with palm tree
    No. 14117 The Alameda (road) with carriages and billboards
  - Miscellaneous, non-Stanford images, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Forest/mountain scene [not a true photograph]
  - Palo Alto Stock Farm - horses, Beautiful Bells, circa 1890 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    No. 12777, No. 12779, and No. 12781 (all same image)
  - Palo Alto Stock Farm - horses, Electioneer, circa 1890 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    No. 12654, No. 12776, No. 12780 and No. 12782 (all same image)
  - Palo Alto Stock Farm - horses, Monbell, circa 1890 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    No. 12778
  - Palo Alto Stock Farm - horses, Nozote, circa 1890 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    No. 12783, No. 12784, and No. 12785 (same image)
  - Palo Alto Stock Farm - panorama, circa 1890 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    This one has Berton Crandall’s stamp, but it is actually an enlargement of center section of Hill & Watkins image in Box 1 folder 20
  - Phi Delta Theta fraternity, circa 1895 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    No. 12904
    No. 12905
  - Stanford residence, Palo Alto, circa 1890 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    No. 12830 Side wing with lawn and statuary
    No. 12831 Lion statue in grounds
  - Stanford residence, Palo Alto, circa 1890 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    No. 12765 Front of house & statuary
    Driveway and front of house with lawn (unnumbered)
  - Student groups - Class of 1895, circa 1895 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    No. 12885 Class on steps of Roble Hall; students (and one dog) wearing mortar boards
    No. 12886 Class on steps of Roble Hall; students (and one dog) wearing mortar boards - slightly different image than 12885
  - Student groups - Sigma Nu fraternity, 1894-circa 1895 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    No. 12894 Group portrait circa 1895
    No. 12895 Group portrait, 1894, names on reverse (different image than 12894)
    Arnold, E. H.; Brown, D. E.; Downing, P. M.; Harrelson, W. H.; Hosmer, A. T.; Maynard, R. E.; McDaniels, John H.; Nash, Frank C.; Rose, Walter M.; Sheehan, John Francis, Jr.; Smith, Lewis H.; Straight, H. R.; Wilson, Jas. F.
  - Student (male) group, circa 1895 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    No. 12557 no id on group
  - View of Stanford University over Lake Lagunita, circa 1891 (Box 4, Folder 7)